Linjian Ma

+1 217 979 7114 \diamond lma16@illinois.edu \diamond linjianma.github.io github/Linkedin: linjianma

RESEARCH STATEMENT

My research interests lie in the intersection of numerical algorithms, high performance computing, quantum simulation and machine learning. In particular, I'm now focusing on developing efficient algorithms for tensor networks with applications in data analytics and quantum simulation. In addition, I'm also working on optimization and efficient compression methods of neural networks.

EDUCATION BACKGROUNDS

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

August 2019 - Expected 2024

August 2018 - May 2019

PhD, Computer Science, Advisor: Edgar Solomonik

Area: Scientific Computing

University of California, Berkeley

MEng, Computer Science, Advisor: *Michael Mahoney*Major GPA: 3.94/4.0

Track: Data Science & Systems

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign August 2016 - May 2018

MS, Mechanical Engineering, Advisor: N.R. Aluru

Concentration: Computational Science and Engineering

Zhejiang University August 2012 - June 2016

BE, Energy Engineering, Advisor: Tao Wang and Zhongyang Luo
Graduate with Honors, Chu Kochen Honors College
Ranking: 1/155

EXPERIENCES

Lab for Parallel Numerical Algorithms, UIUC

August 2019 - Now

GPA: 3.97/4.0

Research Assistant, Advisor: Edgar Solomonik

Topic: Tensor decomposition, automatic tensor differentiation and their applications

Wave Computing & Berkeley AI Research (BAIR)

May 2019 - August 2019

Machine Learning Intern, Advisor: Sylvain Flamant

Topic: Compressing large scale neural networks based on second order information

RiseLab, UC Berkeley

August 2018 - May 2019

Research Assistant, Advisor: Michael Mahoney

Capstone project: Second order optimization of neural network learning

Lab for Parallel Numerical Algorithms, UIUC

May 2018 - July 2018

Research Intern, Advisor: Edgar Solomonik

Topic: Pairwise perturbation and multigrid in alternating least squares for tensor decomposition

Beckman Institute, UIUC

August 2016 - December 2017

Research Assistant, Advisor: N.R. Aluru

Thesis: A multiscale model for the oxide ion conducting and proton conducting solid oxide cells

SKILLS

Programming Languages C/C++, Python, Go, Bash, Matlab, CUDA

ML Frameworks Pytorch, Tensorflow

PUBLICATIONS

- [1] Navjot Singh, **Linjian Ma**, Hongru Yang, Edgar Solomonik, Comparison of Accuracy and Scalability of Gauss-Newton and Alternating Least Squares for CP Decomposition, arXiv:1910.12331 [math.NA], October, 2019. [link]
- [2] Sheng Shen, Zhen Dong, Jiayu Ye, **Linjian Ma**, Zhewei Yao, Amir Gholami, Michael W. Mahoney, Kurt Keutzer, Q-BERT: Hessian Based Ultra Low Precision Quantization of BERT, arXiv:1909.05840 [cs.CL], September, 2019. [link]
- [3] **Linjian Ma***, Gabe Montague*, Jiayu Ye*, Zhewei Yao, Amir Gholami, Kurt Keutzer, Michael W. Mahoney, Inefficiency of K-FAC for Large Batch Size Training, arXiv:1903.06237 [cs.LG], March, 2019. [link]
- [4] **Linjian Ma** and Edgar Solomonik, Accelerating Alternating Least Squares for Tensor Decomposition by Pairwise Perturbation, arXiv:1811.10573 [math.NA], November, 2018. [link]
- [5] **Linjian Ma**, Pikee Priya, and N. R. Aluru, A Multiscale Model for Electrochemical Reactions in LSCF Based Solid Oxide Cells, *Journal of the Electrochemical Society*, 2018, 165: F1232-F1241. [link]

PRESENTATIONS

- [1] **Linjian Ma** and Edgar Solomonik, Accelerating Alternating Least Squares for Tensor Decomposition by Pairwise Perturbation, *Scientific Computing Seminar*, 26th September, 2019, Champaign, IL.
- [2] **Linjian Ma** and Edgar Solomonik, Accelerating Alternating Least Squares for Tensor Decomposition by Pairwise Perturbation, *Scientific Computing Seminar*, 6th March, 2019, Berkeley, CA.
- [3] **Linjian Ma** and N.R. Aluru, A Multiscale Model for the Reactive Mechanisms in Proton/Oxide Ion Conducting Solid Oxide Cells, *PIRE Monthly Meething*, 31st August, 2017, Champaign, IL.
- [4] Linjian Ma and N.R. Aluru, A Multiscale Model for the Oxygen Reduction and Oxidation Reactions in LSCF Based Solid Oxide Cells, 14th US National Congress on Computational Mechanics, 19th July, 2017, Montreal, Canada.

HONORS AND AWARDS

Computer Science Gene Golub Fellowship, UIUC	2019
Graduate with Honor, ZJU	2016
Meritorious Winner, Mathematical Contest In Modeling (MCM)	2015
National Scholarship for Undergraduate, ZJU	2014
The First Class Scholarship for Outstanding Students, ZJU	2013 - 2014
The First Prize in China Undergraduates Mathematical Contest	2013